Hi everybody. Today is Friday, September
12th, 2025 and
our new friend John Kyaku is here.
Welcome, John, to the
>> Thank you. Thank you, Nema. So glad to
be with you.
>> Yeah. Please subscribe and hit the like
button to reach more people. And John, I
want to start with what has happened in
the United States which somehow was so
much shocking to the people. What has
happened to Charlie Kirk? He was they
call him a far right but he was somebody
in my opinion that he when you criticize
his sort of opinion he was listening to
the people. He was trying to communicate
with the people.
>> Exactly. Right. And everybody was trying
to picture him as the far left, far
right. And Netna came out said that it's
the Islamist killed him. Then then he
was asked if Israel was behind it. He
said no it it wasn't Israel. But it's
all about speculation on part of the
people who is more interested in
geopolitical issues one in domestic
issues. Everybody was picturing Choliker
in his own point in in his sort of point
of view. But what is your understanding
of this phenomenon in the United States?
Because after all, I would argue that he
was a very important
>> character in the in today's
situation that we're witnessing in the
United States,
>> especially with young people and most
especially with young conservatives. You
know, it's funny to me how many people
my age, I'm 61. How many people my age
who had never heard of Charlie Kirk and
I say, "Really? How's that even
possible? You've never This guy created
the youth movement for Donald Trump. He
came out of the out of the Tea Party
movement, the anti-ax movement and uh
created this organization Turning Point
USA where he would target uh university
campuses and promote Trump's uh MAGA
conservative message. He became very
very important in contemporary
Republican politics. It was amazing to
me. I've said before and I I'll say it
again to sort of lay some groundwork. I
probably disagreed with Charlie Charlie
Kirk on I don't know 90% of the issues,
75% of the issues, I don't know. But
what you said about him is exactly true
and it's why I actually had respect for
the guy because he was always interested
in dialogue. That's what these campus
events were. People saw them as
provocative. I didn't see them as
provocative. I saw them as engaging. So,
for example, he would say something that
is that's unpopular among um
progressives, but he would want to
engage in a talk, in a debate, in a
dialogue about uh about the issue,
whatever it was, trans rights or, you
know, anything, whatever it was,
education.
Um, in the days following his
assassination,
Stanford University's Center for the
Study of Extremism came out with a poll.
It's a poll that that shows almost
identical numbers to four other polls.
And those numbers show that 34%
of American college students advocate
violence against people whose opinions
they don't like.
That makes me ashamed to be an American.
The country, the Constitution is founded
on the pillar of freedom of speech.
Whether we like or dislike each other's
positions, we should be able to go to
our deaths to protect the right to
express those positions. And to have
fully onethird of college students say,
"No, I would rather kill you than listen
to your position on an issue," I think
is one of the most dangerous things I've
heard in my lifetime.
As you know, uh the alleged killer was
caught um either last night or this
morning. Uh he is 22 years old. He hated
Charlie Kirk. He fits perfectly in this
34% that we're hearing about. And now
the process is going to do what the
process does. We'll see what happens.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
>> John, shifting the gear to what's going
on in the Middle East before the whole
situation with Charlie Kirk, which
somehow overshadowed what has happened
>> in the Middle East.
It was a somehow it was I talked with
with the case of Charlie it was shocking
but
that was after what has happened in the
Middle East with the case of attack on
Qatar. Qatar is one of the most
important one of the most critical
allies of the United States in the
Middle East which after all Israel has
decided to attack them. Donald Trump. It
seems that he knew about it. The
administration said they they informed
the United States before attacking them.
How what do you make of what's going on
in the Middle East with the case of
Israel?
There's literally nothing good that we
can possibly say about this decision. I
mean, there's nothing good we can say
about the genocide that's taking place
in Gaza or the slow motion genocide and
ethnic cleansing taking place in the
West Bank.
You know, I think that everybody has a
right to criticize, for example, the the
murder of civilians in Lebanon
uh or or elsewhere besides Gaza and the
West Bank uh even in Yemen.
But then the Israelis have the
unmititigated Gaul to attack the country
that is not just host to peace talks
but also host to the largest American
air force base on the planet.
The shame here and this is this is why I
think that this is so dangerous. The
shame here is that Donald Trump did
nothing to protect the Qataris. nothing.
At the very least, fire some Patriot
missiles to intercept the rockets coming
in from the Israelis.
And I would like to ask the Saudi
government, where were you when these 15
uh Israeli fighter jets were crossing
your territory?
Why didn't you stop them? Why didn't you
scramble jets? Why didn't you try to
shoot them down? Because you hate Qatar
that much?
because you want to preserve the ability
to join the Abraham Accords that much.
The day that the Israelis attacked uh
Qatar,
I said on my own podcast,
I'm not sure that the White House
understands just how important this is.
All of the Arabs are looking at us
saying, "What are you going to do about
this?" Right? The Qataris have major
non-NATO ally status which means they're
not members of NATO but as a member of
NATO would be we have to defend them.
It doesn't say in the agreement we have
to defend them against Iran. Iran's not
going to attack the the Kataris. We have
to defend them. Well, the attack was by
the Israelis. So why didn't we defend
them? Finally, today in the Washington
Post and the New York Times, there are
questions like what what's the benefit
for the for for Qatar to be an ally of
the United States if the United States
is just going to stand by and allow them
to be attacked?
So if I were Amir Tamim,
I would give very serious thought as to
the future of this alliance because if
if I'm the leader of this country and
I'm not getting anything out of this
partnership, then I would just rather be
left alone and let somebody else worry
about it.
We know that they were attacking the
negotiations room in which they were
trying to negotiate and we don't know
what has happened. Why did they let
leave the room before the attack?
>> Right.
>> There's some rumors that they Turkish
intelligence somehow managed to inform
them or it was somehow by accident.
>> Mhm. They they got lucky and they
but when you look at the behavior of
Israel in terms of we had the same sort
of attitude on their part when they were
negotiating the United States was
negotiating with Iranians if and their
officials to bring some sort of sanity
to what's going on in the Middle East
with the case of Iranian nuclear program
and all of that and they attacked Iran
and right now it seems to me John that
Donald Trump is somehow
It's some sort of they're gambling. They
don't have a strategy. They don't they
somehow the Israelis managed to convince
Donald Trump and his administration to
trust them to let them do whatever they
want to do in the Middle East in order
as they the Israeli ambassador to the
United States said they're changing the
face of the Middle East. But I don't see
that face is changing.
>> No. and and and and the change would
benefit them in a long run.
>> How do you see that?
>> I agree with you. They're killing a lot
of people, but they're not changing the
face of the Middle East. What they're
doing is they're turning the West
against them. You know, here in the
United States now, a majority of members
of the Democratic Party, a majority,
more than 50% support the Palestinians.
It's now split among Republicans. But
but the Israelis are losing the American
voter because
their strategy is just to kill as many
people as they possibly can. Look what's
happening with uh with the Gaza
Palestinians and these these rumors or
leaked reports that the United States
and the Israeli and the Israeli
government are talking to the Albanians,
the Malaysians, the Indonesians.
uh to just move all Palestinians out.
That is the actual legal definition of
ethnic cleansing. That's a war crime.
It's a crime against humanity. You can't
do it. Every time Donald Trump says we
have this wonderful program to turn Gaza
into the next Monaco, actually it's
going to be better than Monaco. That is
a war crime.
You can't do it. And then the US
response is to put sanctions on the
international criminal court or to put
sanctions on the United Nations special
uh interlocutor for u for uh
counterterrorism and refugees and and
everybody else. It's just wrong. If
you're a president of the United States
who has his heart set on winning the
Nobel Peace Prize, you don't win the
Nobel P Peace Prize by encouraging war
and attacks on civilians and the murder
of women and children and non-combatants
and the ethnic ethnic cleansing of an
entire people. That's not how you win
the Nobel Peace Prize. You know, the
Israelis say all the time about what
great support they have, but look at a
map of the world. They don't have great
support. They have support among Western
countries that are allied with the
United States, but there are 144
countries around the world that already
recognize Palestine.
You know, we act like when we see
reports Canada's going to going to uh
recognize Palestine or Australia or or
Ireland, people say, "Oh my gosh,
Palestinians are going to get
recognition." They already have
recognition.
>> It's the West that's late to the game.
And I can't help but to think that as
these Western countries fall like
dominoes
and recognize Palestine, that the
Israelis very quickly are going to
finally realize that they're standing
alone. not really alone because they
have the United States behind them, but
alone to the point where they're not
going to be able to accomplish this
change in the construct of the Middle
East like they say is is underway. I
agree with you, Nema. It's not underway.
The only thing that they're
accomplishing, quite literally, the only
thing they're accomplishing is just
widescale murder.
Do you John when you look at their
attack on Iran, do you think the main
objective of that attack was regime
change? Was something or something else?
What's your understanding on that?
>> I do think it was regime change because
the the Israelis benefit from chaos just
like the Israelis benefited from chaos
surrounding the fall of Saddam Hussein,
the overthrow of Saddam Hussein. Um, but
if you are an anti-Iran westerner,
your only conclusion was the overthrow
of Saddam Hussein served the interests
of Iran.
Well, the only reason we overthrew
Saddam Hussein was because the Israelis
demanded that we overthrow Saddam
Hussein. And I'll add something. I was
in the CIA for a long time and literally
every single time that Benjamin
Netanyahu came to the United States over
the course of decades, he would ask
whomever happened to be president,
"Please attack Iran. Please attack Iran.
Please attack Iran." And every president
said, "No, I'm not going to attack Iran
just because you want me to." Until
Donald Trump.
So they can put they can put lipstick on
a pig, as the saying goes, and say,
"Well, we only did it because Iran is an
existential threat to Israel. They have
this uh this nuclear program. They're
going to build a nuclear uh bomb and
they're going to launch it on Israel."
No. If I were the Iranians, I would say
that Israel is an existential threat to
me and I need a nuclear program as a
deterrent because it's the Israelis who
bomb me. I haven't bombed the Israelis.
It's the Israelis that have an arsenal
of whatever it is 200 220 whatever uh
nuclear uh nuclear devices.
So, this is something this is something
that most Americans just don't
understand. There there really are two
sides to this story. And it's not the
Iranians who are who are militarizing
the Middle East. And may I come back to
something that you said a moment ago
about uh about Doha, the bombing of
Doha?
I I just don't understand how it is that
senior American policy makers couldn't
come to the conclusion
that Israeli actions are going to make
American foreign policy exceedingly
difficult. As I said, if I were Amir
Tamim,
I might be angry enough to say, "You
need to get out of this air force base
enough. We brought you here to to
protect us. You didn't protect us. You
have to leave." I was living in Bahrain
when I was there from 1994 to 1996.
And the Qataris asked us,
they said, "If we build a an enormous
navy base, would you move from Bahrain
to uh Qatar?" And we said, "No, we can't
because we've been in Bahrain since the
70s and we're very, very close to the
Bahraini government and we just can't do
it." And they said, "Fine. How about if
we build the world's biggest air base?"
And we said, "Hey, that will take.
That's why we're there.
Not because you know there's nowhere
else. We can spread out around all over
the region if we want. But the Kataris
invited us and in part it was to protect
them
and we failed to protect them. So why do
the Israelis get a pass? Because you
know if Iran bombed Qatar, which would
of course never happen in a thousand
years, but if that were to happen, the
United States would have been launching
missiles and fighter jets at Iran within
an hour.
So why not protect our friends and
allies against the Israelis? There's
going to have to be a price that comes
with this decision.
I think I think we are living a very
important
you know the changes that are happening
in the Middle East in the west Asia not
only there but in Europe in the eastern
part of Europe what's going on John we
are seeing the rise of bricks SEO summit
>> you look at China today their military
their economy so powerful
>> the war in Ukraine put Russia in a far
better position that they were before
the war started.
And you see the United States, I look at
the United States policy in the West
Asia, in the Middle East, which is so
much important for the security
>> of the world.
>> Yeah. For the world. It's the heart in
my opinion.
>> And you see these stupid decisions on
the part. You remove just two or three
leader of Hamas, leaders of Hamas. How
is that going to change? You attack
Yemen. What? How is that going to change
the policy of Houthies? You kill the
prime minister of Yemen. You know, I
cannot bring I cannot find any strategic
mindset behind behind what's going on
with the Trump administration. We were I
was hoping I was one of the people who
was somehow hoping that the new
administration would bring some sort of
fresh air to the foreign policy of the
United States,
>> right?
>> Which is not happening and it's not
going to happen.
>> No. No. There are no big thinkers. Marco
Rubio is not going to go in history as
the big thinker who conceptualized this
new American foreign policy. He's just
it's not going to happen.
Steve Wyoff, who I'm sure is a very nice
man, is not going to be the big
strategic thinker who solves all of the
problems that the United States has in
the Middle East. And then at the same
time, you have Benjamin Netanyahu
who knows that he has so much political
support in the United States, in the
Congress. He has he has so much
bipartisan support covering both the
Democrats and the Republicans that he
can do anything he wants, anything. And
with Apac and the Israel lobby in the
United States, if you are a member of
Congress and you don't tow the Israeli
line, they will primary you. They'll
spend millions of dollars and they will
defeat you and you won't be in Congress
next year. And so it's like people are
held hostage. our our political system
is held hostage by this by this little
tiny country of European settlers that
just decided they're the ones that have
the rights to this land because God told
them so.
It's just not it's not realistic.
That's why there's never going to be
peace. I I don't think not not if the
status quo uh isn't changed. You made
another important point and I think this
is something that the American
government really does not understand.
Nema is the advent of the bricks uh
countries. I think that the United
States initially initially thought that
the creation of bricks was a joke for
what we call outcast countries to band
together.
These are some of the biggest economies
in the world. China, Russia, India,
Brazil. We should be worried and we
should be very worried at talk of a
unified currency. If the BRICS countries
come up with a unified currency like the
euro and oil producing countries,
whether they're in the Middle East or
elsewhere, begin selling oil in that
currency, the dollar is done and the
United States is no longer the global
hedgeimon.
Another point too, and I'm I'm
disappointed that people in the
mainstream media aren't talking about
this, and that is the misuse and the
overuse of sanctions.
There used to be this joke at the CIA
where we're going to add sanctions
against Iran. I remember saying one
time, "How many more sanctions could
there possibly be? We've been
sanctioning Iran since 1979." Well, now
the sanctions are nonsensical.
You know, they say, "Well, there's an
Iranian guy and he's the head of this
lab and so he's not going to be allowed
to open a bank account in the United
States." Okay. Well, he doesn't want a
bank account in the United States. So,
your sanctions are meaningless. We've
gotten to the point where we have so
many sanctions on so many people in so
many countries that they just don't
matter anymore. I went to China last
year and um
I wanted to buy something. I wanted to
buy souvenirs for my kids and nobody
would take a Visa card, but they would
take this thing called the octopus card.
I never I never heard of this thing
before. So I asked one of the
shopkeepers, "What is this octopus card
you guys take? I can't I can't buy
anything with my Visa card. I have to
pay cash." And he said, 'Yeah, the
Octopus card is the Chinese credit
card.' I said, 'Why don't you just use
Visa card? And he said, 'Ah, because
every Visa card transaction goes through
New York and makes us liable to American
sanctions. The Octopus card goes through
Shanghai, so we don't care what the
Americans think. And I said, Aha,
that makes sense. And it also shows the
weakness of the United States because if
the Chinese are able to attract other
countries like the countries in bricks
into a China based financial system,
the US control of international banking
is done. And that's where we're headed.
When we talk about Israel, many people
argue that these are very smart people,
very smart organizations in each and
every part of the government. But
looking at the behavior of Israel so
far,
how much of that sort of smartness,
intelligence comes out of their action?
You see, they have failed in Iran. And
if it wasn't because of the United
States and the attack that Donald Trump
somehow attacked Iran to put an end to
the conflict, that's why he attacked
Iran.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
You look at Yemen, even Donald Trump has
decided to go to the Red Sea and back
down. And they said he said that they
capitulated and all this.
>> No. Yeah. No, they didn't. But how
Israel, when it comes to Israel, how do
you find these people who are smart, who
know what they're doing? And how do they
believe that they're going to get
something out of these stupid bit
decisions that they're making? In your
opinion,
>> I think that politically
they're smart in their short-term uh
actions and objectives. you want to you
want to get a pro-Israel candidate
elected, you put a million dollars into
the campaign. You put TV advertisements,
you're going to get that person elected.
But over the long term, Israel is
becoming more and more conservative,
more and more militarized to the point
where convicted
criminals,
criminals convicted of hate crimes are
your most important ministers and
cabinet members.
So, I think that they're they think
they're so smart because they're good at
politics.
The the opposite is true in terms of uh
Israeli foreign policy. They've put
themselves into a box where even the
most pro-Israel
European countries are saying, "Well,
the Israelis have gone too far. We have
to say something at the United Nations.
We have to send a message through the
ambassador. Enough is enough." So, I I
think that I think that this incremental
move to the right actually hasn't been
that incremental over the last couple
years. I think it's been a very hard
hard move to the right. It's alienating
a lot of people, especially in Western
Europe and among Democrats in the United
States. And the Israelis are approaching
a point of no return where they're going
to turn enough people against them that
they're not going to be able to
guarantee their own safety no matter how
many people they kill. And another thing
too,
I am a Greek Orthodox Christian, a
practicing Greek Orthodox Christian.
Greek Orthodoxy is one of the oldest
faiths in the world. One of the oldest,
it's the oldest denomination in
Christianity.
And I will not sit by while the Israelis
bomb St. Borfidio's church in Gaza, for
example, the oldest continuously
operating church on the planet
where there are 24 women and children
inside who have taken refuge. The
Israelis bomb this 1600year-old church
and kill everybody inside. And I'm
supposed to say what? That I support
Israel?
Not a chance.
This is a problem in the United States
where you have Zionist evangelical
Christians and Zionist conservative
Catholics
who ignore the mass murder of
Palestinian Christians
in the name of what? helping uh Jesus
come back uh at the end of time because
all the Jews have returned to who knows
what their odd, you know, crazy ideology
is telling them. But this is
unsustainable. It's untenable. We're
getting to the point where it's all
going to fall apart and the Israelis are
blind to it.
John, they have managed a huge network
of spies in Iran before the attack.
>> Yes,
>> it was huge. Look at what has happened
in Iran. It was somehow shocking in the
initial hours of the attack on Iran.
>> Yeah.
>> How how do you find how could they
manage that? It was all because of
Afghanistan with the the situation in
Afghanistan.
>> That was a big part. Yeah, that was a
big part. You know, people ask me all
the time if I would talk about the the
best intelligence services that I
encountered over the course of my
career. That's an easy one. But among
the worst is the Iranian service.
>> And and I'm not blaming the Iranian
government. What I'm blaming is the fact
that the West has so isolated Iran for
such a long time that they don't have
these natural highlevel relationships
with other intelligence services that
can train them in things like counter
intelligence which is a very big problem
for the Iranian government. Right now,
the government is completely infiltrated
by by spies. Not because these spies
have any love of Israel, but because
they need the money, and money is always
the greatest motivator to convince
people to commit espionage. Well, if
you're an Afghan refugee that has no
money and no home and no medical care,
no no uh no way to make your life better
and you have no formal status in Iran.
And this Mossad person comes up to you
and says, "Hey, I'll give you $100 a
month if you tell me what time this
scientist who lives in this building,
what time he leaves every day, what time
he comes home every day, and which route
he takes when he leaves." That's very
important intelligence and it only cost
$100.
And so the the Israelis have been very
good in exploiting poor, desperate
people
to work against the Iranian government,
even if they don't realize that they're
working against the Iranian government.
Even if they don't have a desire to work
against the Iranian government, that's
how cynical the Israelis are. The
Iranians need to work with the Russians
and the Chinese and others on
counterintelligence. They need to
tighten up the flow of information uh in
Iran. There was another uh uh incident
that we learned after the Israeli
bombing of Iran. You know, the Israelis
have had this active program to kill
Iranian scientists for years. And so we
learned after the most recent bombing
that the scientists were not permitted
to carry cell phones. Great. great idea,
but their bodyguards were carrying cell
phones. And so rather than target the
scientist, you just target the bodyguard
or you target the wife or you target the
daughter. The Israelis, I said this in a
speech last night here in Washington,
the Israelis, if they want to target one
person and they think that one person is
in an apartment uh building, they will
blow up the entire city block and kill a
thousand people if they think they're
going to get that one scientist.
So don't underestimate the viciousness
of the of the Israeli Mossad. Protect
yourself and you protect yourself
through good trade craft. Carrying a
cell phone is very bad tradecraftraft.
That's just one example. Um, not being
able to take care of refugees is bad
tradecraftraft because it allows
an opening for the Israeli Mossad to
move in and exploit uh, refugees. The
Iranian government, of course, doesn't
have money to be able to handle all of
these refugees. Maybe this is something
you talk to the Chinese about. The
Chinese have lots of money. Maybe you
engage with the Chinese intelligence
service to advise on how to tighten up
counter inelligence so that the Israelis
don't have free reign to infiltrate the
government and then to bomb the people
who are, you know, the most important to
the government. It's it's a long road.
It's going to take 20 years, but they
have to start now.
>> Do you feel that Israel would attack
again? Would attack Iran? They said that
they're going to attack Qatar. At least
what they've learned from the the
reactions from the their talk in the
aftermath of the attack on Qatar. They
said, "We're going to go find these
people each and everywhere. It doesn't
matter which country is that,
>> we're going to attack them." I
>> I was on a show a couple of days ago in
which I debated the former IDF
spokesman. And um you can't debate
Israeli officials, either current or
former. They they don't let you speak.
They they throw out lie after lie after
lie. They accuse you of being a
terrorist or of supporting terrorism.
And uh I finally I had to say to this
guy, I will put my career up against
yours any day of the week. And I said
the first thing I I said was literally
everything you said in your in your
opening statement was a lie. The Muslim
Brotherhood has never been classified as
a terrorist organization. Never. Not by
anybody.
You can dislike somebody's politics,
that doesn't make them a terrorist
organization, as one example.
So,
one of the things the Israelis are
really good at is being so inflammatory,
and I mean this especially in the United
States, they're so inflammatory in their
in their rhetoric
that they make any questioning of
Israeli policy an act of anti-semitism.
I'll give you an example.
my partner and I, my partner is uh an
Iranian-American woman, and we went out
to visit friends of ours uh in rural
Virginia here in the United States. The
husband is Iraqi American, the wife is
Iranianamean,
and we decided to stop for lunch in this
little tiny village,
um just a little pizza restaurant. And
so she and I are sitting in a booth and
behind me are two American hillbilly
fat, no teeth, you know, fat
hillbillies.
And I said to her,
"Do you really think the Israelis will
bomb Iran again? I hope not because it's
just going to get worse and worse."
And this fat guy right behind me turned
around and said, "Um,
do you support genocide,
genocide of the Israeli people?" And I
turned around, and I never respond to
idiots like this, but I couldn't help
myself. I got so angry. I turned around
and I said, "This fight did not begin on
October 7th.
It got so bad so quickly that we had to
get up from the table to fight
and the owner of the restaurant came and
threw him out.
But this is what we deal with in the
United States. Most Americans are so
stupid or so ill-informed or so
misinformed or so liable to Israeli
propaganda
that they just believe what they're told
to believe. They don't look at these
issues analytically.
Israel is good. Palestine is bad. Israel
likes Christians.
Palestine hates Christians. despite the
fact that, you know, 10% of Palestinians
are Christians, most of them are in the
United States now. But this is what
we're up against. The Israelis have been
so successful, not just in the United
States, but in other Western countries,
at propagandizing the citizenry that
it's going to take decades to roll that
back. And it's going to take a lot of
money.
I think
John you you've mentioned you work with
you know MSADA you know Israel how does
it work do you feel that is there any
alternative in Israel to replace the
government the current prime minister of
Israel that would make some sort of
changes because we've heard Naftali
Bennett saying thing then the same sort
of mindset who's who's alternative in
Israel who's going to make peace who's
going to change the force in Israel.
>> I I don't think peace is possible. And
I'll tell you why. The the Labor Party
in Israel, it for all intents and
purposes, it it no longer exists. It
ruled Israel for decades, and now it has
like five or six members in the Knesset.
Starting in the in the very late 1980s,
Israel saw a massive influx of Jews from
Russia and Ukraine. And these Jews
tended to be much more conservative than
the earlier generations of Jews that had
gone to Israel after the Second World
War.
And so I don't think there are any
voices for peace in Israel. If there
are, they're silenced. I think if
anything,
at least in this current Israeli
government, I'm I'm going to smile as I
say it because it sounds so ridiculous,
but Benjamin Netanyahu is probably the
most liberal member of the current uh
Israeli government. That's how
outrageously
right-wing, dangerously right-wing this
government is in Israel when Benjamin
Netanyahu is the most leftwing.
Uh, and the other thing too is let's say
public opinion really does change. Let's
say a miracle happens and the United
States decides it's not going to support
Israel anymore and it cuts off aid to
Israel, cuts off military aid to Israel
and Western Europe cuts off military aid
to Israel. The Israelis aren't just
going to give up and walk away. They're
not going to allow themselves to circle
the drain and go down the drain. They
have 200 plus nuclear weapons
and they've said that they'll use them.
So I'm I'm not in any way optimistic
about peace. I don't think there is any
current Israeli political figure who
would be serious about about peace.
how we know in Syria the situation is
much more complicated that we thought
and before because it seems that Israel
and Turkey are fighting each other in
Syria so bad because it's somehow
the United States is there trying to
somehow supporting trying to manage
trying to support Israel more but
I wouldn't be surprised John, with what
has happened in I wouldn't be surprised
tomorrow I wake up and see Israel and
Turkey are attacking each other. There
is nothing else to be shocked in the
Middle East because everything that
could have shocked me before has already
happened.
>> And what position would that put the
United States in? because Turkeyy's a
NATO country and if Turkey invoke
invokes um um
the the word is escaping me uh chapter 5
whatever it's called uh of the of the
NATO treaty all of NATO would have to go
thank you article five of the treaty um
every NATO country would have to go to
Turkeykey's uh Turkeykey's rescue
against Israel
>> but you you're right and you make an
important point here Nema
where for like a minute there was this
very close cooperation in Syria between
the United States, Israel, and Turkey.
Now, they all did that for a different
reason. The the Israelis wanted Assad
out. Uh the Turks wanted some sort of
victory over the Kurds. And the United
States just I don't know what the heck
we wanted. It's impossible to even
figure out what the policy is from one
day to the next. um they hated Assad,
but but Assad was really the only thing
protecting the Christian community uh in
in Syria. So whether you liked his
politics or not, in my view, Assad was a
force for stability.
And then he was gone in just a matter of
a week or two. He's just gone. So now
what? The Turks got what they wanted uh
as far as the Kurds and what really
amounts to a deacto buffer zone uh along
the border.
uh the United States got what it wants
in that it pretty much handpicked the
the new leader of the uh of the Syrian
government and immediately lifted
sanctions and then blessed him with a
high level state department visit and
Syrians are dancing in the streets but
the Israelis are bombing Syria.
What the heck happened? You didn't want
Assad despite the fact that a lot of
scholars were saying, "Listen, the devil
you know is better than the devil you
don't know." And they knew that they
could contain Assad. They knew it. So
why roll the dice and take the chance
that somebody who was a member of
al-Qaeda
and the co-founder of the Islamic State
is going to be the new leader of the
country? Is it that the Israelis didn't
expect that Donald Trump would just
decide one day, I like this new guy. I'm
going to lift sanctions. I'm going to
recognize him. I can work with him. The
Israelis had to say, what? That's not
what we expected. But the Israelis were
responsible for it. They knew Assad.
They knew him for decades. They knew
they could contain him. So why push him
out?
I think there is a lot for the United
States to decide about the Middle East
specifically when it comes to because
the whole
we we can assume what has happened so
far in the Middle East with the changes
I I think Russia and China it's a huge
opportunity for Russia and China to come
in
>> and to make connection with these Arab
states. Remember what China and Russia
behind the scene did to Iran and Saudi
Arabia. Behind the scene they have
prepared them. They talked to each other
rar between the two countries which was
>> out of
I don't know if if the United States and
John when it comes to the United States
do you feel that there is establishment
running the show? Do you think that the
president of the United States has
something to do with that? Because after
all, we have to think of it. There is no
difference between the Biden
administration and the Trump
administration.
>> None. None whatsoever. And you know, I
I've told this I've said this many times
before in interviews, but when George W.
Bush was president, we used to say at
the CIA all the time that we never saw
an administration work so hard to not
talk to our enemies.
Why? Why do you have a State Department
if you don't allow them to talk to
anybody?
And so Donald Trump, as much as I
disliked Donald Trump, when he opened
talks with the North Koreans, we
celebrated like finally we're going to
start talking to our adversaries. We
should be talking to the North Koreans,
the Iranians, the Russians, the Chinese,
the Cubans. We should be talking to all
these countries. That's what diplomats
do. They talk, but we don't. Well,
behind the scenes, the Russians were,
the Chinese were, and the next thing you
know, the Saudis and the and the
Iranians are are normalizing relations.
The Bahrainis and the Iranians are
normalizing relations. That's called
diplomacy.
And if you want to be
the hegeimon
and the country that calls all the
shots, you have to engage in diplomacy
because both sides have to show that
they won something. And the United
States doesn't do that. We say you you
do this or else sanctions, maybe
bombings. That's not diplomacy.
That's defeatism.
And so you're right. And this is an
important point that you make. It
doesn't matter who's in the White House.
Whether it's a Democrat like Joe Biden
or a Republican like like George W. Bush
or Donald Trump. It just doesn't matter.
We want every country to do exactly what
we tell them to do. And if they don't
like it, sanctions. Well, we've gotten
to the tipping point where they say,
"Now, you know what? We don't care about
your sanctions." And if you're cutter, I
would be on the phone to the White House
saying, "Don't you ever do something
like that again. You're either going to
protect us or you're out."
So, we'll see where that goes.
I think, John, when it comes to the
Middle East, the United States needs to
needs to at least consider do two
countries, two important countries,
Turkey and Iran. Mhm. Without question.
>> And we have other players in the Middle
East, but these are two major players.
>> Who do you feel that the United States
is capable of changing the the sort of
mindset they have toward these two
countries? I see Turkey part of you
mentioned Turkey is part of NATO, but
when it comes to weapons, you remember
the United
>> No. Yeah, that's right. That's right.
You know,
>> they have to go and buy it from Russia.
>> You know what, Nema? The only reason
Turkey is still a part of NATO is
because when they wrote the NATO charter
in 1947, it never occurred to them that
they might have to throw a country out.
And so there is no provision in the
charter to throw a country out. So
unless unless Turkey withdraws from NATO
like the French did in the 70s,
the rest of NATO is stuck with them.
>> That's it. They're in NATO. But you're
exactly right. Turkey is a regional
power. Iran is a regional power. And so
really what the United States should do
is to rely on Turkish diplomacy. Maybe
Turkey should be the middleman, right?
They have the ability. They're
wellplaced. They have a gigantic
military. They have a strong enough
economy and they live there in that
neighborhood.
So yeah, why are we not counting on this
on this NATO ally
to help us engage with Iran or with, you
know, the Syrians or No, well, not the
Syrians, that's a bad example. Uh or
with the Palestinians or or whomever.
And then on top of all that, we make
very stupid, unnecessary mistakes.
There's a famous quote from Gamal
Abdaser, the former president of Egypt.
I actually had it hanging over my desk
in at the CIA
and I've I've researched this so I know
that it's true. I found the the actual
speech. But he said this. He said, "The
thing about you Americans is that you
never make clear-cut stupid decisions.
You only make complicated stupid
decisions." Which then makes us wonder
if there's something about them that
we're missing.
And it's so true.
Yeah,
>> that's he just described American
foreign policy.
So why don't we rely on the Turks? Why
don't we tell the Israelis, "Wait a
minute. Wait a minute. You can't bomb
Iran. We're engaged in talks with Iran
right now.
Let us deal with the Iranians. We'll try
to negotiate something." That
conversation never took place.
We just said, "Oh, Netanyahu wants to
bomb Iran. Okay. All right. Oh, the
bombs didn't do enough damage. Okay,
we'll bomb Iran, too. What is that?
That's not foreign policy.
It's amazing. Yeah,
I
I I was just when I was thinking of
Israeli attack on Iran and the whole
regime change mindset, that could
somehow be used to convince the Trump
administration. But when it comes to
attack on Yemen,
>> prime minister together with the whole
cabinet members were assassinated
>> and these people you look at Yemen
today, these people
>> somehow they have nothing to do. We
cannot say nothing to do but they're not
that much connected with Houthies.
>> No, no, not at all.
>> You bring pain to Houthies by attacking
the government in Yemen.
>> You know,
>> I'll tell I'll tell you something funny.
I' I've been to Yemen five times. The
first time I went, there were two Yemens
uh uh the
Yemen Arab Republic and the People's
Democratic Republic of Yemen. And then I
went right after unification, people
were literally dancing in the streets
because they had uh joined and unified
one Yemen. The third time I went, things
aren't going very well. The fourth time,
they're firing Scud missiles at one
another. The fifth time was so dangerous
that an armored convoy had to take me
from the airport to the hotel to the
embassy and then back to the airport. Uh
but you're right, the Houthies are a
minority in uh in Yemen. Oh, I know why
I was telling you this. So, the last
time the last time I went I I arrived in
Sana from Djibouti.
little a little five minute plane ride
to Djibouti and I was in a taxi.
I wasn't supposed to be you're only
supposed to take armored cars, but I
like Yemen and I speak Arabic and so I
wanted to go to the Suk and uh just look
around. So I said to the taxi driver,
"So how are things going with uh with
the Houthis?" And he said, "Oh, we're
we're fighting the Houthis every day,
but the Saudis are helping us with their
drones. They bomb the Houthis all the
time. And I said, "The Saudis don't have
drones." And then I said, "Oh my god,
we have drones in Djibouti." And then I
just stopped talking. So I went back. I
was working on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee at the time and I
said to John Kerry, he was the chairman.
I said, "Did you know we're bombing
Yemen with drones? There was no
congressional vote to allow us to bomb
Yemen." and he said, 'Yeah, that's
that's something that's above your pay
grade. Don't talk about that.
That's American foreign policy.
But I'll tell you, I I I have friends
who are in the the Trump White House
right now, and and the way they explain
the administration's policy toward Yemen
is is kind of funny to me.
You mentioned that they came to this
agreement with the Houthis and declared
victory, right? So they were just angry
that the Houthies the Houthies had fired
rockets or sent drones to fire rockets
at American um military ships. Well, how
can you not see that it's an American
military ship? It's all painted gray and
it's completely covered in rockets and
missiles and guns and has the American
flag flying. So the deal was
you stop attacking our ships and we'll
stop bombing you. The Israelis were
furious because the Israelis wanted us
to bomb the Houthis at every
opportunity. We don't have a fight
uh with the Houthis. We just don't have
a fight. You know, it's funny. My first
time that I ever went to Yemen, I was
meeting with the American ambassador who
was a lovely old man. He was a diplomat.
He he died many years ago now. But I
said to him, "Ambassador, I have a
question. It's a real question, not a
rhetorical one. what national interests
do we have in Yemen? And he went like
this.
None.
We don't have any national interests
here.
And you know what? Even all these years
later, that was 1990. I asked that
question. Even all these years later,
except for the security of the Babal
Mandeb,
>> we we don't have national interests in
Yemen. What we should be doing is
digging water wells, helping them build
roads or hospitals,
upgrade the electrical grid, but that's
never going to happen.
John, I think with the war in Ukraine
and what has happened between somehow
Iran and Israel, we can argue that
major wars cannot be
cannot be the main policy in Washington
because of the conflict in Ukraine. You
cannot afford. You go to Ukraine, you
bring everybody there and you you're
trying to put everything there and after
all you cannot provide the way you
cannot produce the way that Russia is
producing weapons. That's why you're
failing. You're
>> That's right.
>> They did everything. Ukrainians, I think
after all, we have to see Ukraine. They
fought so well. They did everything to
>> defeat Russia. They couldn't do it.
>> Couldn't do it.
>> Yeah. You go to China the same way. I
think the somehow do you feel that the
the policy of in Washington in the west
is somehow shifting from
new wars to new coups, new new
>> probably color revolutions.
>> Sure. But that's very, very dangerous
because you never know what it's going
to look like at the end. And this is a
problem that I've always had with
American foreign policy. And I saw it
with my own eyes when I was on the
seventh floor of the of the CIA. I was
the executive assistant to the CIA's
deputy director for operations.
It's easy to invade a country. It's
easy. It's easy to to overthrow a
government, but it's very very difficult
to get out. And so, as a result, I mean,
just take Iraq as an example. We killed
a million Iraqis,
most of whom were civilians. We lost
5,000 American troops. Was it really
worth it for what? for for the
anti-American chaos that we left behind.
Was it worth it? We have nothing to show
for it. And that's really American
policy. We always have an idea of how we
want to attack a country and there's
never a clue how to get out or how to
define what victory looks like. So, I
agree with you. color revolutions are
probably cheaper than spending500
billion dollars on military assistance
to uh to Ukraine. But still, what does
that look like in the end? If if the
past is any guide, it doesn't look like
anything that benefits the United
States.
>> I think there is a lot to be learned
from the behavior of China.
>> They're buying allies. They're buying
partners. They're making new friends.
>> They're doing everything.
>> The Chinese, this is a master class in
diplomacy that the Chinese are showing
the world. The Chinese have one foreign
military base.
I've been there because they share it
with us. It It used to be called Camp
Lemon in Djibouti. There's a there's a
fence that goes right down the middle
and one side is Chinese and the other
side is American. We have
191 military bases in 144 countries. So
why did the Chinese have a 300 mph
bullet train? Why did the Chinese have
better roads? Why did the Chinese have
nicer airports? Why did the Chinese have
have a strangle hold on uh on global
shipping? It's because we spend all of
our money on weapons.
So, you're right. The Chinese know how
to do this and they know how to win and
we should be taking a lesson from the
Chinese.
>> It was a great pleasure, John, to talk
with you.
>> Pleasure was mine. I'm so glad we got
the chance to meet. I've been looking
forward to this for a long time.
>> I'm going to talk I'm going to contact
you. We're going to continue these sort
of talks and fantastic thing. There is a
lot to learn from you. you have a lot of
knowledge from the Middle East from
what's going on.
>> Thank you so much.
>> In terms of the West Asia and the huge
problem that geopolitical problem that
we're facing today's in the Middle East
in
>> May may may I shamelessly plug my my two
podcasts. Um if people I have a daily
podcast called Deprogram. It's on
YouTube and Rumble. DProgram with Ted R
and John Kiryaku. And then I have one
that's a little bit deeper look at these
exactly these issues called deep focus
with John Kuryaku. So thank you very
much
>> John. You you can send me the links. I'm
going to put it in the description of
this video.
>> Fantastic. Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you.
>> Great pleasure John.
>> Thanks for having me.
>> See you soon. Bye-bye.
>> Bye bye. Bye.